Werner Seligmann Papers
Werner Seligmann Papers
1948-1998
1955-1998
Seligmann, Werner.
95 linear ft.
Project material (drawings, plans, elevations, perspectives, photographs and slides), memorabilia (clippings, scrapbooks), and writings of the American architect, urban designer, and educator.
2732655
Biographical History
Werner Seligmann (1930-1998) was a German-American architect, urban designer, and educator.
Werner Seligmann was born in Osnabrück, Germany in 1930. Surviving the Holocaust, he emigrated to the United States in 1949 and was naturalized in 1955. He married the former Jean Liberman of Cortland, New York in 1954 and had two children, Sabina and Raphael. In 1961 he founded Werner Seligmann and Associates, Architects and Urban Designers (WSA). He died in 1998.
Seligmann received his bachelor's degree in architecture from Cornell University in 1955. He spent the next two years as an instructor at the University of Texas at Austin as one of the "Texas Rangers," a group of architects that also included John Hejduk, Lee Hodgden, Bernhard Hoesli, Colin Rowe, John Shaw, Robert Slutzky, and others. He completed his graduate study at the Technische Hochsschule in Braunschweig, Germany and then taught at the Eidgenössiche Technische Hochschule (ETH) in Zürich, Cornell University, and Harvard University.
He served Syracuse University first as the Dean of the School of Architecture, 1976-1990, then as Distinguished Professor of Architecture until his death. In addition, he held several other appointments including Thomas Jefferson Professor of Architecture at the University of Virginia School of Architecture. He was a juror, guest lecturer and visiting critic at several institutions and received numerous awards throughout his career for his work. In 1998 he was awarded the Topaz Medallion for Excellence in Architectural Education from the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture (ACSA) and the American Institute of Architects (AIA).
Influenced by Frank Lloyd Wright and Le Corbusier, Seligmann was known for his synagogues, public buildings, housing, and urban design work in the central New York region. His major built works include: Beth David Synagogue, Binghamton, NY; Science Building II, State University of New York, Cortland; Temple Brith Sholom, Cortland, NY; Ithaca Scattered Site Housing - Elm Street (also known as West Village) and Maple Avenue (also known as Maple Hill Apartments), Ithaca, NY; Willard State Hospital Administration Building, Willard, NY; Olean Central Fire Station, Olean, NY; Ithaca Commons Center (also known as Center Ithaca), Ithaca, NY.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Werner Seligmann Papers span the years 1948-1998 (1955-1998 bulk) and are arranged in two series: Projects and Writings and Biographical Material. The collection comprises drawings, presentation boards, slides, models, photographic materials, specifications, competition programs, newspaper clippings, articles, reports, studies, monographs, and scrapbooks.
There is very little material regarding the business or financial aspects of Werner Seligmann and Associates, Architects and Urban Designers (WSA) or Seligmann's personal or faculty life. No employee or job lists were found. The bulk of material is project related and represents all phases of the architectural process, in particular the design development and construction phases. Documented are Seligmann's built and unbuilt projects and the competitions he participated in under WSA or with colleagues and students.
Seligmann-assigned project names, abbreviations, and job numbers were often used inconsistently. Project names created during the processing of these papers for those projects with no discernable names are noted with an asterisk. Completion dates for built works or competition dates are assigned if determined.
Seligmann's work from the mid 1950s into the 1960s includes private residences and businesses, a few competitions, and one major built religious work, Beth David Synagogue in Binghamton, New York. The papers also include a few drawings from his 1955 thesis work at Cornell University, a proposed hotel for Cortland, New York.
Most of the material dates from the late 1960s through early 1970s, highlighting the public and urban design work of WSA. Major clients include the Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA), the New York State Urban Development Corporation (UDC), the New York State University Construction Fund, and the New York State Health and Mental Hygiene Facilities Improvement Corporation. Major built projects completed during this period include Temple Brith Sholom, in Cortland, Ithaca Scattered Site Housing (Elm Street and Maple Avenue), the Science Building II (SUNY Cortland), and Willard State Hospital in Willard, New York. He also worked on several small residential projects, most notably a residence for astronomer Carl Sagan, which was not built.
The material from the mid 1970s to 1998 centers on residential and business projects and work for the municipalities of Olean and Ithaca, New York. Major works built during this period include the Olean Central Fire Station, the North Barry Street Community Building, also located in Olean, and the Ithaca Commons Center. In the 1980s and 1990s he entered several national and international competitions.
The strength of this collection lies in the many original sketches on trace for competitions such as the Arizona Historical Society and Museum, the Cardiff Bay Opera House, the Felix Nussbaum House, the National Museum of Korea, Roosevelt Island, and the Topography of Terror. Original sketches also exist for a few private residences and major projects such as Ithaca Commons Center, Olean Central Fire Station, and Temple Brith Sholom.
Projects (1948-1998; bulk 1955-1998) includes drawings, presentation boards, photographic materials, specifications, competition programs, newspaper clippings, articles, reports, studies, correspondence, slides, and models. Some of the material is in German or Italian and is noted in the inventories. Drawings may be duplicated in a variety of formats throughout the collection. Project not built are noted as "(not built)" and project type is given in square brackets, e.g. "[Government]".
Projects are further broken down by type of material. Drawings (span dates: 1948-1993) consists of approximately 6,200 plans, elevations, sections, perspectives, axonometrics, maps, studies, sketches, preliminary, presentation, working, mechanical, electrical, structural, landscaping, and as-built drawings. Models (not dated) exist for Beth David Synagogue, Congregation Beth Sholom Addition, East Syracuse Library, Felix Nussbaum House Competition, Rosefsky Summer House 4a, b, Temple Brith Sholom and the Willard State Hospital Rehabilitation Center. Presentation boards (span dates: 1955-1993) vary in size up to three by nine feet and comprise photographs, site maps, descriptive text, and drawings. Project materials (span dates: 1954-1998) includes professional photographs, snapshots, negatives, positives, or photocopies of the site or drawings. May also include sketches, small presentation boards, specifications, competition programs, newspaper clippings, articles, reports, studies, correspondence, or other miscellaneous items. Approximately 4,400 Slides (span dates: 1955-1987) depict plans, elevations, sections, perspectives, referential images, earlier existing structures, interiors and exterior views and details, analytical or explanatory drawings, models, construction, and some text.
Writings and biographical material (span dates: 1966-1998) includes published and unpublished magazine articles and newspaper clippings by or about Seligmann and his work, lists of competitions and exhibitions, awards and honors, page layouts for proposed book, and a videotape of the American Institute of Architects Topaz Award Introduction and text of Seligmann's acceptance speech. The five monographs on architecture are located in the Department of Special Collections. Arranged by date or project.
Arrangement of the Collection
Project materials are arranged alphabetically by project. Drawings, housed in tubes 1-177, are arranged by project. Presentation boards 1-89 are arranged by project. Slides are arranged alphabetically by job name. Although box numbering appears to run from Box 1 to Box 95, there are in fact only 83 boxes; boxes 5, 7, 21, 27, 32, 33, 39, 41, 43, 49, 56, 68, 69, 71, 73, 74, 75, 77, 78, 80, 83, 84, 85 have been consolidated as file folders within Box 95.
Related Material
has more than thirty collections relating to architecture, including the papers of Marcel Breuer, Pietro Belluschi, William Lescaze, and Richard Neutra. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Published monographs on Seligmann have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Seligmann, Werner.; Werner Seligmann and Associates.; Architects -- United States.; Architectural design.; Architectural design -- Competitions.; Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th century.; Architectural firms.; Architectural practice.; Architecture -- Designs and plans.; Architecture United States History 20th century.; Architecture, American.; Architecture, Domestic.; Church architecture -- United States.; City planning -- United States.; German Americans.; Synagogue architecture.; Architectural drawings (visual works); Blueprints (reprographic copies); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Detail drawings (drawings); Exterior perspectives.; Interior perspectives.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Schematic drawings.; Sketches.; Slides (photographs); Specifications.; Architects.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jean L. Seligmann,
Inventory
- Project records
  - A.V. ZOGG AUCTION PAVILION (ZAP) McGraw, New York (not built) [Commercial], proposed addition to serve as an auction pavilion
    - Drawings, 1963; working drawings (Tube 1)
    - Slides, models; 8 (Box S-1)
  - ARIZONA HISTORICAL SOCIETY MUSEUM DESIGN, COMPETITION, Phoenix, Arizona (1985) (not built) [Cultural]
    This was a major competition for new historical society museum. Sponsor/client: Arizona Historical Society.
    See also Writings and biographical material: Scrapbook II.
    - Drawings, undated; presentation drawings (Tube 2)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 3)
    - Presentation board 20, sections, elevations, "3."
    - Presentation board 21, plans, section, elevations
    - Project material, 1985; sections, elevations, plans; correspondence; competition materials; report of jury (Box 10)
    - Slides, title slide, site plans, elevations, perspectives, sections, plans, earlier existing structures, analytical or explanatory diagrams, referential images; 75 (Box S-1)
  - ASH COMMUNITY CENTER, See NORTH BARRY STREET COMMUNITY BUILDING Olean, New York.
  - BAILEY RESIDENCE ADDITION (BAR) Cortland, New York (1963) [Residential], kitchen remodeling and porch addition
    - Drawings, 1963; working drawings (Tube 4)
    - Slides, general views; 4 (Box S-1)
  - BANCROFT RESIDENCE REMODELING*, Cortland, New York (not built) [Residential], small basement remodeling project
    - Drawings, undated; working drawings (Tube 5)
    - Slides, models; 2 (Box S-1)
  - BELLARDINI PROJECT, Cortland, New York (not built) [Commercial], existing barn remodeling project
    - Drawings, 1973; studies, base drawings (Tube 6)
  - BELLEVUE METHODIST CHURCH (not built) [Religious]
    Sponsor/client: Bellevue Methodist Church. Collaborators/partners: Employing Architecture Firm: Sargeant, Webster, Crenshaw & Folley (Syracuse)
    - Project materials, 1958; sections, plan, perspective (Box 95, Folder 78)
  - BENJAMIN FRANKLIN ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, See FRANKLIN SCHOOL PRE-KINDERGARTEN RENOVATION, Binghamton, New York.
  - BETH DAVID SYNAGOGUE (BDS) 39 Riverside Dr., Binghamton, New York (1963) [Religious]
    Small orthodox synagogue. Sponsor/client: Congregation Beth David. Collaborators/partners: Consulting Engineer: Edward A. Fassler
    See also Writings and biographical material: Scrapbook I; Writings and biographical material: Miscellaneous.
    - Drawings, 1962; working drawings, perspectives, sections, elevations (Tube 7)
    - Drawings, 1962; working drawings (blueprints) (Tube 8)
    - Model, poor condition; approximate dimensions: 12"L x8"W x3"H (Box Model-1)
    - Model, poor condition; approximate dimensions: 12"L x8"W x2.5"H (Box Model-4)
    - Presentation board 22, photos of interior, plans, elevation, perspective, axonometric, working details, sketches, (dated 1962)
    - Presentation board 23, First and second floor plans
    - Project material, undated; photos of exterior and interior (Box 13)
    - Project material, undated; plans, elevations, sections, perspectives on original [Newspaper box] (Box 13A)
    - Project material, 1961; plans, elevations, sections, perspectives on original [Newspaper box] (Box 13B)
    - Project material, 1962; various schemes, sections, elevations, plans, model, interior details; sketches (Box 14)
    - Project material, 1961-1966; construction, exterior and interior; article, newspaper clippings; anniversary journal; text from exhibition board (Box 15)
    - Slides, Title slide (dated 1962), site plans, axonometrics, design sketches, elevations, perspectives, section, plans, construction, artistic works, models, facade, exterior and; 255 (Box S-1)
  - BIDDLE RESIDENCE ADDITION AND RENOVATION* East Lake Road, Skaneateles, New York (not built) [Residential]
    Update of residential addition and proposed studio addition. Arnold Konrad (original designer, 1956). Sponsor/client: Richard and Jean Biddle. Collaborators/partners: Construction: Paul Yaman Construction
    (Alternate names: Miller Summer Residence)
    - Project material, 1963-1964; snapshots of model and construction (Box 57)
    - Project material, 1995-1996; working details, plans; sketches; correspondence; financial; work orders; notes; product information (Box 76)
  - BINGHAMTON CITY HALL RESTORATION, Binghamton, New York (not built) [Government]
    Urban design proposal. Sponsor/client: Valley Development Foundation (VDF). Collaborators/partners: Engineers: Galson & Galson Consulting Engineers, Inc. (East Syracuse)
    - Drawings, 1976; plans, working details (Tube 23)
      See also Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA) - General: Drawings.
    - Project material, 1972; site plans; photos of exterior and interior; report (Box 18)
    - Slides, site plans, perspectives, sections, plans, earlier existing structures; 45 (Box S-1)
  - BINGHAMTON COURT STREET AREA STUDY, Binghamton, New York (not built) [Government]
    Sponsor/client: Valley Development Foundation (VDF)
    - Drawings, undated; façade proposals, elevations, text (Tube 9)
    - Project material, 1974; site plans, section, elevation; report (Box 19)
    - Slides, site plans, sections, elevations, earlier existing structures; 15 (Box S-1)
  - BINGHAMTON COURT STREET BRIDGE RAILING, Binghamton, New York (undated) [Government]
    Bridge railing replacement. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA).
    See also Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA) - General.
    - Drawings, undated; working drawings (Tube 10)
    - Project material, undated; working drawings, elevation (Box 31)
    - Slides, elevations, sections; 4 (Box S-1)
  - BINGHAMTON URBAN RENEWAL AREAS 1 AND 2* Binghamton, New York (not built) [Government]
    Various urban design proposals. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA). Collaborators/partners: Photographer: C. Hadley Smith (Ithaca)
    - Model, city bus details (oversize), 1970 (Box 24A)
    - Project material, undated; site plan, elevation, axonometrics, perspectives, sections, model; Midtown Shopping Mall schemes (Box 24)
    - Slides, perspective, models, street furniture; 75 (Box S-5)
  - BINGHAMTON URBAN RENEWAL AUTHORITY (BURA) - GENERAL* Binghamton, New York (not built) [Government]
    Variety of projects done for Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA) as urban design consultant. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA). Other projects related to BURA include the Binghamton Court St. Bridge Railing; Binghamton Urban Renewal Areas 1 & 2*, Broome Co. Cultural Center Competition, Chenango River Promenade, Fowler's Dept. Store Entry*, Memorial Bridge, Washington Street, Woodburn Court Proposal, and Valley Development Foundation (VDF).
    - Drawings, undated; presentation drawings, composites, negatives (Tube 11)
    - Drawings, 1974; sections, elevations, plans, composites, detail sheets, base map (Tube 12)
    - Drawings, 1975; plans, elevations, axonometric studies (Tube 13)
    - Drawings, 1970-1973; presentation drawings, base and site maps, working details (Tube 22)
    - Drawings, 1969-1971; preliminary and presentation drawings (Tube 177)
    - Project material, 1968-1970; site plans, section, reports (Box 81)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1967), plans and drawings, elevations, general views, proposals by other architects, Seligmann lecture, report; 225 (Box S-5)
  - BIRMINGHAM CULTURAL CENTER, COMPETITION* Birmingham, Alabama (undated) (not built) [Cultural]
    Large urban facility with convention hall and theater. Sponsor/client: City of Birmingham (AL).
    - Presentation board 17, site plan, plans, sections, text, perspectives, vehicular and pedestrian circulation diagram (two connected boards); "237."
    - Presentation board 18, site plans, perspective, sections, plans, covered pedestrian plan (two connected boards); "260."
    - Presentation board 19, text, perspectives, sections, plans, covered pedestrian, parking, traffic plans (two connected boards)
  - BRADLEY RESIDENCE Corning, New York (1955) [Residential]
    - Project material (Box 94B)
    - Project material, 1954-1955; plans, sections, perspective, exterior and interior (Box 95, Folder 27)
    - Slides, plan, construction and reconstruction, general views, side views, interior details; 60 (Box S-1)
  - BREWER-TITCHENER CORPORATION (BTC), Cortland, New York (not built) [Commercial]
    Remodeling of locker rooms and plant manager's office. Sponsor/client: Brewer-Titchener Corporation. Collaborators/partners: Engineers: Galson & Galson Consulting Engineers, Inc. (East Syracuse).
    - Drawings, 1975; working drawings (Tube 14)
    - Project material, 1975; plans (Box 28)
    - Slides, plans, models; 6 (Box S-1)
  - BRIGHTON BEACH MIDDLE-INCOME HOUSING Brooklyn, New York (1968) (not built) [Residential]
    Major housing competition. Sponsor/client: NYS Housing and Development Authority; Brooklyn/NY Chapters of AIA
    - Project material, 1968-1969; record of submissions and awards; letter (Box 95, Folder 80)
  - BROOME COUNTY CULTURAL CENTER, COMPETITION One Stuart Street, Binghamton, New York (1967) [Cultural]
    (Alternate names: Broome County Veterans Memorial Arena)
    Seligmann served as competition advisor, wrote program and competition brief, supervised the jury. Winning scheme, submitted by ELS Architects, was built. Sponsor/client: Broome County, NY.
    - Drawings, undated; base drawings, site maps, elevations, sections (Tube 15)
    - Project material, 1967; elevations, plans, model, site, map; sketches; correspondence; competition materials (Box 16)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1966), models, miscellaneous; 60 (Box S-1)
  - BUFFALO WATERFRONT URBAN DESIGN STUDY Buffalo, New York (not built) [Government]
    Academic work done in the Cornell University Urban Design Studio. Sponsor/client: City of Buffalo. Collaborators/partners: Associated Architects: Colin Rowe, J. Alan Wells.
    - Project material, 1969-1971; brochure, article (Box 95, Folder 77)
  - CAMP HUNTINGTON, See HUNTINGTON CAMP DORMITORY (HUCADO) Raquette Lake, New York.
  - CAPRI THEATER IMPACT STUDY Binghamton, New York (not built) [Cultural]
    Urban design study of possible conversion of the Capri Theater. Sponsor/client: Valley Development Foundation (VDF).
    - Drawings, 1975-1976; site plans (Tube 16)
    - Project material, 1976; site plan, working details; impact study (Box 17)
    - Project material, oversize (Box 94B)
    - Slides, site plans; 5 (Box S-2)
  - CARDIFF BAY OPERA HOUSE, COMPETITION (CBOH) Cardiff, Wales (1994) (not built) [Cultural]
    Major international competition. Sponsor/client: Cardiff Bay Opera House Trust. Collaborators/partners: Associated Architects: Mark Shapiro.
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 17)
    - Drawings, undated; sketches (Tube 18)
    - Drawings, undated; presentation drawings, hardlines, underlays, base maps (Tube 19)
    - Project material, 1991-1995; perspective; sketch; correspondence; competition materials; financial; clipping; exhibition catalog (Box 72)
    - Slides, site plans, perspectives, sections, plans, working details, other competition entries; 5 (Box S-2)
  - CENTER ITHACA, See ITHACA COMMONS CENTER Ithaca, New York.
  - CENTRE CULTUREL DU CONGO BELGE, COMPETITION Congo (Belgian Congo) (1958) (not built) [Cultural]
    International competition. Sponsor/client: Belgian Congo.
    - Drawings, undated; sections, elevations, plans (Box 1)
    - Drawings, 1958; sketch overlays (Tube 20)
    - Slides, elevations, sections, plans, general, interior, and back views; 20 (Box S-2)
  - CHENANGO RIVER PROMENADE, Binghamton, New York (1968) [Government]
    Project includes walkway, planting, public amenities. Sponsor/client: Binghamton Urban Renewal Authority (BURA)
    - Drawings, 1968; elevations (Tube 21)
    - Drawings, undated; site plan, elevation, section, plan, axonometric (Box 23)
    - Slides, site plans, elevations, perspectives, sections, working details; 20 (Box S-2)
  - CONGREGATION BETH SHOLOM ADDITION (BSC) Rochester, New York (not built) [Religious]
    - Drawings, undated; design studies (Tube 24)
    - Model, poor condition; approximate dimensions: 24"L x16"W x3"H (Box Model-3)
    - Project material, undated; plan (Box 55)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1972), model; 50 (Box S-2)
  - CONGREGATION BETH SHOLOM CHEVRA SHAS (CBS, CBeSh) Jamesville, New York (not built) [Religious], new synagogue
    - Drawings, 1970; design studies (Tube 25)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1968), site plans, elevations, sections, plans, models; 25 (Box S-2)
  - CORTLAND COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY LIBRARY (CHS, CCHM) 25 Homer Ave., Cortland, New York (1974) [Cultural]
    New library, storage, reading room. Sponsor/client: Cortland County Historical Society. Collaborators/partners: Mechanical: Galson & Galson Consulting Engineers, Inc. (East Syracuse); Construction: Woodford Brothers, Inc.; Photographer: Alex. F. Ross (Philadelphia)
    - Drawings, 1973-1974; working drawings (Tube 26)
    - Project material, 1976-1980; plan, section, elevations, interior and exterior; financial (Box 29)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1978), elevations, sections, plans, general, interior, and back views; 60 (Box S-2)
  - CORTLAND FIRE STATION REHABILITATION (CFS) 19 S. Franklin, Cortland, New York (1978) [Government]
    Renovation and restoration of existing fire station. Sponsor/client: City of Cortland. Collaborators/partners: Structural: Snyder Burns & Associates (Syracuse).
    - Drawings, 1976-1978; working drawings (Tube 27)
    - Slides, title slide (dated 1972); 1 (Box S-2)
  - CORTLAND YWCA ALTERATION, Cortland, New York (not built) [Government], addition of fire stair
    - Drawings, 1963; working drawings (Tube 28)
  - CORTLANES BOWLING CENTER 391 State Rd. 13, Cortland, New York (1961) [Recreational]
    (Alternate names: Cort-Lanes)